[Music]
hey hey welcome back you made it it is
day
five it is the final day of the final
week
uh of the coding camp uh you should
really pat yourself in the back just for
getting this far honestly there's a
big drop off in the camp and we lose
people
as it goes uh so i'm back here again
today and no surprise with my campers
i'll go and let them introduce
themselves so i'm here with my campers
again today oh what nice looking shirts
you have
it's the connecting with code 2021
orange
very nice all right go ahead and
introduce yourself hello my name is
keegan fisher
and you hi i'm mckinley
you guys ready for your last day yes
super duper
so today's actually going to be kind of
fun we're going to do a project called
advanced kaleidoscope and the first part
is going to be regular kaleidoscope and
mckinley is going to teach it
but first i'm going to introduce kind of
what we're doing uh so the thing we're
doing is a kaleidoscope so that's a fun
word to say that's for sure
and there's a solution here which i
thought was already up but it now is it
up
so the way the solution works is it will
ask you
how many sprites would you like so this
is kind of part of the advanced thing
i'm going to say that i want five
sprites and what it does is it lets you
use the arrow keys
to move around your five sprites and you
can use left and right
to kind of make neat patterns and things
like that
it of course doesn't have to be five so
if you run it again
it'll ask you how many sprites would you
like let's say i want
i don't know 40 sprites so it'll make 40
individual sprites and now when you do
it
it'll actually kind of move all 40 which
admittedly kind of always look like
circles
you can also do a thing where you can
switch the costumes so you can kind of
like change everybody's color
to make another neat pattern and things
like that so it's a it's a neat program
you can do a lot of like crazy shapes
and things with it you've probably seen
like some of mckinley's
patterns but she does these crazy
kaleidoscope things
so that's the goal today it's kind of
meant to be a little bit shorter
uh is is the hope um and we're going to
also kind of test you
uh on a couple things so the first thing
we're going to do is we're going to
build what i consider a
regular kaleidoscope and then we're
going to have you turn it into like
using clones and things like that
so for regular kaleidoscope i'm actually
going to have mckinley come up
and she's going to lead us through this
this is going to be the same if you
happen to work
week one this is going to be the same as
what we did on day five of week one
so we're gonna do that together and then
we're gonna make it into advanced uh
version
all right mckinley come on up it's all
yours hi my name is mckinley fisher in
case you've forgotten
and i'm going to be building the uh
kaleidoscope code so the first thing you
need to do
is go to scratch.mit.edu
and then create a new game and your
screen should look like this
the first thing you're going to do
is to delete the cat sprite
and add a new sprite
this new spray is going to be ball
and your bell sprite should have shown
up on
on the screen and then
um we're gonna start with a green flag
when green flagged
clicked
and then we are going to choose
what direction it's pointing in so
we're gonna have this ballpoint in
direction zero
so it's a pointing straight up
and then we're gonna have it go to zero
zero the exact
middle of the screen
once you do that you're going to
go into control and find a forever loop
okay so i zoomed in a little so you
could um see better
and so this is our code so far when
green flag clicked point in direction go
to
x0 y0 and then a forever loop
in that parabola loop you're gonna put
four if statements
inside of those if statements you're
going to go to sensing
and put in a key space
press for each of them
once you do do that you're going to
change
space to up
down left
and right arrow key
[Music]
once you do that you're going to go back
up to motion
so that you can actually move
and for the up arrow key you want to
drag in a move
10 steps so now if you were
to run your program and press the up
arrow key your ball would move
but no other keys would work
we're actually going to change that 10
steps to 3
and we're going to do almost the exact
same thing for the down arrow
except that we're going to do negative
three steps
now if you run your program your balls
should be able to go down
and up
for left arrow key you're gonna um you
see
these two turn blocks the one that is
turning
left 15 degrees you're going to drag
into the left arrow
you're going to change that 15 to 5
and then for the right arrow you're
going to choose the
turn that is turning right and change
that to 5 as well
now if you run your program you should
be able to move your ball around
however you would like
now that's great but it's quite a bit
boring so we're now we're going to make
the
kaleidoscope part of it to that to do
that you have to go into extensions
and your screen should um look like this
and you're going to click on the pen
so now you see that opens um got you
some new blocks
so the first block that you're going to
drag in from this new
area is erase all
and you're going to put that at the very
top
or it could be underneath point
direction and go to
your choice now you're going to put a
stamp
under the move 3 and so now if you run
your program
it should leave a trail
so that's the first step of your
kaleidoscope
now this is optional but you can put a
stamp block
under the backwards arrow so that way if
you move
backwards it'll also leave a trail that
is completely
optional to you so now you should be
able to move your ball around and it
should leave a colored
trail and that looks pretty good but now
we're going to add two more balls
to do that you're going to click on the
ball and you're going to click on
duplicate so now you should have a
second ball
and you're gonna duplicate it one more
time and
you should have three balls in total
now the first thing you're going to do
to these other balls is
you can change the color of all your
balls
so you see that the balls already have
built-in costumes of different colors
for the first ball i'm going to choose a
blue costume
for the second ball i'm going to choose
a green costume and for the third ball
i'm going to choose a purple
and so now you see that my balls are all
different colors
and they should and they all were the
only problem is
is that they're always on top of each
other to change that
you're gonna go um into ball two's
code it's gonna look exactly the same as
the first ball
but there's one modification that we
need to make
so you see this line that says point in
direction zero
that's duplicated from the first ball
you're gonna change that zero
to one twenty and so now if you run your
program you see
you'll see that the green ball moves a
slightly different
um different from the blue ball and the
purple ball because it's pointing a
different direction
at the start you're going to do almost
the same thing to ball three
except that it's going to be negative
120.
if you run your program you should have
a regular kaleidoscope and so
now you can play around with it and that
you can
um you programmed the um regular
kaleidoscope now my dad's going to take
over
and make the advanced kaleidoscope
all right that was that was awesome sis
so she made
a kaleidoscope just like we did last
week and she did it uh
perfectly the only thing that i would
change is i don't take this uh
stamp on the the negative direction of a
difference that mckinley and i have had
for a long time
so everything is working and everything
is good
but you know the advanced version we
want to do more so there's
two reasons we want to make an advanced
version well number one
reason is that we want to make it to
where you can actually
select how many of these balls you want
right so you know you might want to say
seven or something like that and then
you can make seven and now
we don't want to make seven balls right
that would take forever to duplicate
make seven you could also do things like
a hundred right
so you would never want to actually like
duplicate the sprite
99 times and make 100 of them but you
can see that with this version of the
advanced kaleidoscope
you actually can make 100 sprites of
something
and the solution to this duplication is
to clone something
so that's one of the big advantages of
cloning is that you can have as many of
something as you want
the other advantage is let's say that
you did want to make a change to your
code
so if i wanted to make a change to this
code let's say i wanted to take out this
stamp on the negative direction well if
i take it out of one of them
and i go forwards and i turn and then i
go backwards you can see that their code
is actually different right
and so that's another reason that you
prefer clones instead of duplicating
sprites
so here's what i want to do i want to
get it down to where there's only one
sprite again
so i'm going to delete the second and
this third copy
and my goal is to make just this one
sprite be my only sprite in the game
and then to make clones of it the other
thing i'll say is that
since we're using clone tricks you don't
really care about where this ball starts
at all
um in fact you can just kind of like put
it off into space just kind of like
prove that fact
and you can also hide it right because
that's the original we don't care about
the original at all that's a pretty
common trick with clones that
we just hide the original and then also
uh whenever we're dealing with clones we
actually don't use wind green flag
clicks
so i'm going to take that off of when
green flag clicked
and i'm instead going to control and i'm
going to find
when i start as clone and so that's also
another trick that we use for clones a
lot now the thing we've got to remember
is how were the sprites different uh and
the way that they were different was
this
point in direction so the trick we've
used in the past and i'm going to go
ahead and get you kind of started on
this here
is we've made a variable um that we've
like
set and then we've done the clone if you
uh hopefully can kind of remember that
trick so i'm going to make a variable
called
uh the starting direction
and i again use my camel case system for
starting direction and it's going to be
for all sprites
so now what i want you to try to do and
this is going to be a little tricky
i don't really need to show the starting
direction variable
is i want you to see if you remember
some of the skills we've used in this
camp for making clones
and see if you can do it on your own and
so this clone right here
is almost done the only thing he's
missing is a is a show command
i usually like to show it after i do the
go to
but that's because the original is
invisible and then this guy showed
so he is almost done he needs
this point in direction to actually use
this variable
and the thing i want you to just try on
your own it's going to be a challenge
is i want you to try writing the code
that's going to make
three balls and so i want you to make
three balls three clones
and typically where we put code like
that is over on the stage
so you're going to have to you know
make a clone change the starting angle
make another clone change the starting
angle make another clone
change the starting angle if you can i'd
rather you did it with a loop instead of
just three
three of those statements and also
remember there's a little bug to where
you should put a small delay
after you create your clone so take a
minute you can review some old code if
that helps you
but see if you can write the code for
the stage yourself without my help
i'll come back i'll write it in a minute
um but see if you can write it without
your
without my help to make three bowls they
will all be the same color right now
that's okay
but see if you can do that
all right i think my camper's got it
mckinley knocked it out uh no problem at
all uh
keegan's uh not quite his experience uh
i helped him some
but but he did get it um i'm not
expecting you to get it i just wanted
you to try
so i'm going to write it with you so
this is on the stage
so things start when the green flag is
clicked so that's a good way to start
and then what i know i'm going to do is
i know i'm going to repeat something
three times
and the thing i'm going to repeat is
going to involve making a clone
so i'm going to say create clone of ball
uh and then the little bug that we've
kind of learned about is that you need a
small delay
after you create the clone with the
tricks we're using um and so now i just
need to uh if i if i did this uh you
know i could put it on and run it
um but it's going to create three bowls
that are all right on top of each other
right so not quite what i was after uh
if i go into variables what i really
want to do is i want to set
that starting direction to zero at the
beginning
and you can see that the ball has
already used that variable starting
direction
and so i want to set it to zero there
and then i want to change it
after i make a ball so my starting
direction and the amount
i wanted to change it back if you
remember from the simple version uh
is 120 and the reason it's 120 is
because there's three bowls
and all the way around the circle would
be 360. so 360
divided by 3 is 120 so that's how i got
that value
and i'm also going to delete this my
variable just because it was annoying me
so i'm going to delete my variable
variable
i did not delete starting direction so i
just deleted this one
and so now it does what i want and it
actually like makes three clones
and it works kind of like it did before
the only problem that you see now is
that they're all blue
and so we want to do something to make
them not all blue there's a couple
different solutions to this
but i think what i'm going to do just to
keep it simple is i'm just going to
randomly pick a costume i think that's
that's good enough for this step because
we're going to change it later anyway
so go into looks i go into switch
costume 2 and i'm just going to stick it
just before my show here
and you might remember you can address
costumes by their name
or by their number and so if we look at
this ball
we can see that it's got five costumes
and so a good way to randomly pick one
is to go into operators and say pick
random
and so we're going to refer to it by
number and we're going to pick one from
one to five
now this isn't a great solution because
it could have duplicates uh so like
there you know i had two
um yellows uh here i've got two purples
uh there i finally got uh all three
colors the other way you could have
written that is you could have like made
a variable called like
costume number and then you could have
like indexed through it one two and
three
but we're going to change how we want to
do it anyway
cool so things are going really well the
next thing i want to do is going to be a
little
trickier we want to do not just three
balls
but we want to do any number of balls
all right so [ __ ] was jumping out of
her seat because she already figured it
out so i told her that she could show
you how to do it so take it over sis
okay so i have figured out the secret of
making much more balls
how to do is you go to stage and
you see that we already have this code
here you're gonna go to sensing
it has this built-in question that is
very handy for
the type of thing we're about to be
doing so you're gonna
um drag over ask what's your name and
weight
and you're gonna put it at the top of
the code you're gonna change what's your
name
to how many balls
do you want
and then you wait and then um instead of
repeating three times
you're gonna repeat the answer so
like if you put in 26 balls
uh that would be the answer repeat 26
balls to make 26
uh clones of the ball and then um
one last thing with the answer is you
need to go
into operators and define find this
division
sign now you're going to take 360 which
is
um all the degrees in a circle and
divide it by the answer so all your
balls are equally spaced out
and so once you do that it should work
and so if i say 26
balls and i hit enter should make all
those balls and
so um that is how you make
multiple clones of the ball
all right sis you're very clever uh by
the way my son keegan discovered that if
you type in like a bunch of balls like
and you start driving like before it
finishes making them you can kind of
like make a weird stream pattern of them
as well right so there's
there's all kinds of crazy things that
you can do it looks really kind of like
spooky right so
that's great i am totally happy with
that
you can see that it is only picking
these five different colors
this is an optional step that i'm going
to show you next is
you don't have to just use costumes
there's actually more things you can do
with like
looks than just changing costumes so
just to show you that you can do this
there's all kinds of graphic effects
that you can set
and so we're going to set the color
to a random number so instead of
switching the costume
i'm going to set the color to a random
number
i'm going to get this switch costume out
of here because i won't need it
and so i just changed it instead of set
the costume number i'm going to set the
color effect
you can see that there's a lot of
effects that you can do to your sprites
color is what we want here it actually
goes from 1 to 200
i have no idea why it goes from 1 to 200
but i had to look it up and
it apparently goes from one to two
hundred and so now if i put in say eight
bowls
you can see that it'll randomly pick
a variety of colors so it's using uh the
blue as the starting point
and then it's randomly changing it by up
to 200. so if we run it again
it'll be different colors i kind of like
that pattern that looks really good it's
almost like a rainbow
so that is an optional change you can
stick with the costumes if you prefer
but i wanted to show you about how you
can actually change other
graphic effects the next thing i want to
do
if you look at the solution over here is
that it makes a
button to switch costumes so if i said
eight sprites
you know i could do it with eight
sprites but it's got this button that
you can click on and say next
and then it'll switch everybody's color
to the next costume
and we haven't used buttons uh in
sprites uh sorry buttons in scratch
but it's actually pretty easy to do and
i thought that since the camp is almost
over
i'll let show you a button uh so let's
put a button in here i'm going to save
it first
so this is going to be saved as collide
collidoscope
uh advanced uh kaleidoscope is so hard
to spell uh e-i-d-o is the important
part in kaleidoscope
um and so now i'm gonna make that button
all right so i'm gonna make a new sprite
here so the button is actually a new
sprite
and they're actually built in so just
click on choose a sprite just click on
the circle here
um and then you can probably find it i
just want the one that's called
button 2 you can use button 1 or button
3 if you wanted but i'm going to use
button
2. button 2 you can see comes in two
varieties it can be orange or blue i
kind of like the blue the best
and then if you want you can put words
on your button
so i'm going to click on the text here
and i'm going to make
white text so i'm going to switch this
to some white color
and then i'm going to type the word next
and you can see that the word next is
currently a little smaller than the
button
you could fix this one or two ways you
could either make the button smaller
or you could make the text bigger either
one works i think it might be easier to
make the text bigger personally
so i'm just going to make the text
bigger and i'm not worried about the
overall size yet because the size
up here i'm going to change it with the
size that's right here so i can change
the
the whole thing very easily i just
wanted to get the relative size
of the button to the text right so play
around until you're happy with your
button
i think that looks pretty good there and
then i'm going to choose to put it
basically just right up in the corner so
i think that
that looks pretty good if you wanted to
do the lower right corner you could
doesn't really matter
but we've got a button it looks
clickable and so we want to add
code to make it actually be clickable
and buttons what they typically do
in their code is they're they're quite
short
you have a when the sprite is clicked
and typically what you want to do is you
want to tell somebody else that you got
clicked so what they typically do is
they just broadcast a message
so almost every button i've ever made my
whole life like it consists of like
these two lines of code
that's not quite true sometimes it wants
to do something to itself but usually
it wants to tell other people so just
broadcast a message
i'm gonna make a message here uh called
uh next
so whenever i click the next button he's
just gonna broadcast next
so he's just gonna tell the whole world
next right so just
just a way of letting them know the
people that are going to have to listen
uh for this next message are going to be
the balls
so the balls so come into the ball it's
good
are going to have a win i receive next
and what i'm going to do to change their
color again there's many options here
is i'm just going to say next costume
and what that'll do is that'll change it
from the blue to the next color
and then that color effect will have a
different impact on that other costume
and so it hopefully should make all the
bowls change their colors
so i'm going to go ahead and stop it and
run it again here i'm going to say that
i want nine balls
and so now i can see that i've got nine
balls and then when i click on the next
button
uh he broadcast to everybody uh next and
you can see that they all change their
color
so it's kind of a way to uh to have
everybody change their color
and by the way if you wanted the back to
not leave a trace the fun thing about
this code
is these are all clones so you could
just take it out
one time and so i'll do my nine again
and now uh they all won't draw anything
when they go back which which
i like because then i can kind of do uh
crazy crazy patterns right
uh cool i think this is pretty good i
think i might choose to put on a crazy
backdrop
there's one that's kind of like goes
with kaleidoscope yeah raise i think
raise is cool
and so now i can do as many as i want so
i'll do 80
just to kind of finish things off i
could start driving while they're
building that has a neat effect
but i think that i kind of like the the
effect here as well
and then if i click on next all my
colors will change
uh click on next again uh you can see
that you can make make all sorts of
crazy patterns pretty
cool pretty fun click on share
as soon as you click on share it takes
you to this page and we'll just say
tell me how many balls you want
and then use the arrow keys to drive
i'll put an exclamation point on there
so super fun project to share with other
people
so once you get it made make sure you
copy that url uh email it to
friends and family they'll like seeing
it as well
i better check out my campers to see if
they uh they made it through i have a
feeling that mckinley probably did
all right campers did you have fun today
yes all right well
keegan's got some craziness going on all
right let's see it from the beginning he
can hit the green flag
how many balls did you pick nine nine
balls and then click next costume
looks fantastic all right mckinley did
you get yours working as well
yes oh yeah move around that
is so cool and then if i hit next it
goes
to a different costume and then if i hit
the green
green flag i can put in how many balls i
want and move around
looks awesome looks very nice
did you guys have fun this week yes what
was your favorite game is this your
favorite one
yes it's shorter which i know keegan
likes
very nice work uh so that's it for the
camp i want to say a couple things uh
just to wrap up today
uh so first off uh coding is fun you can
do this that's our main message that's
our take home
uh hopefully you've had that drilled
into uh over the last one or two weeks
depending on how long you've been with
us
the other thing i'll say is that your
creativity
is important is as important for what
you can make
as your coding skills so coding skills
are great but you can really see how
scratch like
brings creativity to life so this week
we did a lot of things together let's
just kind of review some of them
we started with the lawn mower we
learned how to do the math to make a
grid and put them all up there
and then we revealed a random backdrop
which was really neat
uh day two was the dino jump that's
where we learned about gravity the guy
throwing the ball off the roof it starts
going faster and faster as it gets lower
we also made that one kind of like a fun
game to play so that was one of our
funnest games to play
the irish sheepdog this one was crazy
this one we
created a timer to see how fast you
could do this task
i don't know if people played it but
using the arrow keys to get that dog
around is kind of hard
and it's really neat to see if you can
go faster and faster we also learned
about a neat concept called pushing
sprites
so in order to push a sprite for one
sprite to push another
really they just need to have the same
direction and the same speed
and then it looks like you're pushing
that sprite which is really fun
the hardest day was actually day four i
told you that it was gonna be day three
but the hardest day was actually day
four
uh we did the slide puzzle we made loops
uh we made lists
um we did some advanced things that day
uh if you got your slide puzzle again
that's a that's a big
pat on the back if you got that one
working uh and then today friday was
kind of a funner day
but really we gotta um learn some new
skills like with user input and that
color effect
um and we gotta reinforce uh the things
that we've been learning throughout this
camp
so how many of these different things
use clones clones clones clones clones
clones
lots and lots and lots of clones all
right so that is
it uh we loved having you join us
we have a lot of fun doing this camp we
hope to do it again next year
um certainly certainly certainly uh fill
out that feedback
just to kind of let us know what's going
on and you're definitely welcome and
encouraged to buy a t-shirt
to kind of remember your experience with
us alright thanks so much
[Music]
bye